Eric M. Fischer

Computer Vision Engineer ericmfischer.com

Background

Purpose: I am a first-year Ph.D. student specializing in artificial intelligence in the Department of Statistics at the University of California, Los Angeles. I carry out generative learning research using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods at the Center for Vision, Cognition, Learning, and Autonomy (VCLA) and am advised by Dr. Song-Chun Zhu.

I earned a Masters from the Department of Computer Science at UCLA and submitted a thesis *Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference*, for which I built a deep generative classifier that utilizes short-run MCMC inference, Langevin dynamics, and backpropagation through time to achieve similar classification accuracy to an analogous convolutional neural network, but with the added benefits that it may generate data, may learn unsupervised from additional unlabeled data, and it exhibits robustness to adversarial attacks, due to the stochasticity of the Langevin equation and the top-down architecture of the underlying generator network.

Before my Masters, I worked as a Full Stack Software Engineer in the San Francisco bay area for over 2 years, most recently at NatureBox in Redwood City. Before this, I attended an advanced software engineering program, Hack Reactor, in San Francisco. I earned a Bachelors from the Department of Philosophy at UCLA. During my Bachelors, I focused my studies on first-order logic and philosophy of language and consciousness.

Research Interests: brain-machine interfaces, neuroscience, consciousness, neural signal processing, reinforcement learning, unsupervised learning, generative learning, Markov chain Monte Carlo methods

Education

University of California, Los Angeles | Ph.D. Statistics

Sep 2020 - current

- Specialization: artificial intelligence
- Advisor: Dr. Song-Chun Zhu

University of California, Los Angeles | M.S. Computer Science

Sep 2018 - June 2020

- Specialization: artificial intelligence
- Advisor: Dr. Song-Chun Zhu
- Thesis: Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference (escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw)

University of California, Los Angeles | B.A. Philosophy

Sep 2009 - June 2013

- Emphasis in first-order logic and philosophy of language and consciousness
- Cum laude honors, UCLA College Honors, Philosophy Departmental Honors, Phi Beta Kappa member

Experience

Center for Vision, Cognition, Learning, and Autonomy | Graduate Researcher | Los Angeles, CA | Dec 2018 - current

• Investigate generative learning research questions with Ph.D. students in research lab (vcla.stat.ucla.edu/people.html)

University of California, Los Angeles | Teaching Assistant | Los Angeles, CA

Mar 2020 - current

- Teaching assistant for courses: STATS 10 Introduction to Statistical Reasoning, STATS 102 Introduction to Monte Carlo Methods
- Grader for courses: STATS 21 Python and Other Technologies for Data Science

NatureBox | Full Stack Software Engineer | Redwood City, CA

Mar 2016 - Dec 2017

- Core contributor to new Flux/React web application after company added direct-to-consumer business
- Led various projects including a payment processor migration, addition of Amazon payments, and a 2nd version of API

Cinemagram | Software Engineer | San Francisco, CA

Sep 2015 - Dec 2015

• Worked with Python, Ruby, and SQL code to construct internal data interfaces and tools

ClearPath Capital Partners | Wealth Advisor Associate | San Francisco, CA

Sep 2013 - June 2014

• Passed Series 65 (Uniform Investment Adviser Law Exam) to acquire securities license as an investment advisor

Publications

Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference | M.S. Thesis | escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw

 Deep generative classifier utilizes short-run Markov chain Monte Carlo inference, Langevin dynamics, and backpropagation through time to achieve similar classification accuracy to an analogous convolutional neural network, but with the added benefits that it may generate data, may learn unsupervised from additional unlabeled data, and it exhibits robustness to adversarial attacks, due to the stochasticity of the Langevin equation and the top-down architecture of the underlying generator network

Learning Multi-Layer Latent Variable Model via Variational Optimization of Short Run MCMC for Approximate Inference | ECCV | contributor (not author) | arxiv.org/pdf/1912.01909.pdf

• Ran experiments for a short-run MCMC residual network that outperforms a variational autoencoder in terms of image reconstruction error and image synthesis quality, while not requiring the design of a separate inference network

Research

Exact and Cluster Sampling of Ising Model | github.com/EricMFischer/exact-and-cluster-sampling-markov-chains

• A convergence analysis comparing exact sampling with the Gibbs sampler and coupled Markov chains to cluster sampling with the Swendsen-Wang algorithm

First-Order Optimization Methods for CNN | github.com/EricMFischer/first-order-nn-optimization

• Custom Python implementations and convergence analyses of first-order optimization methods Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD), SGD with momentum, SGD with Nesterov momentum, RMSprop, and Adam

T-Snake Model for Generative Inpainting | github.com/CS269-Capstone/t-snake-mask-generation

• Employs a topology adaptive snake deformable model to probabilistically generate missing image data

Variational Lower Bound Formulation and Application of VAE | github.com/EricMFischer/variational-autoencoder

• Statistical formulation and analysis of evidence lower bound for the variational autoencoder, using the MNIST dataset

Graduate Coursework

University of California, Los Angeles

STATS 200A - Applied Probability

STATS 200C - High Dimensional Statistics (current)

STATS 201C - Advanced Modeling and Inference

STATS 202B - Matrix Algebra and Optimization

STATS 202C - Monte Carlo Methods for Optimization

COM SCI M276A / STATS M231A - Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning

COM SCI M266A / STATS M232A - Statistical Modeling and Learning in Vision and Cognition (audited)

COM SCI M266B / STATS M232B - Statistical Computing and Inference in Vision and Cognition

COM SCI 247 - Advanced Data Mining

COM SCI 251A - Advanced Computer Architecture

COM SCI 269 - Seminar in Artificial Intelligence: Deformable Models

EC ENGR 236C - Optimization for Large-Scale Systems

EC ENGR 239AS - Neural Networks and Deep Learning

EC ENGR 239AS - Reinforcement Learning Theory and Applications (current)

EC ENGR 243A - Neural Signal Processing (current)

Independent

Hack Reactor, advanced software engineering immersive program in San Francisco, CA, hackreactor.com, June - Sep 2015 CS 224n - Natural Language Processing with Deep Learning, Stanford University on web.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/ CS 230 - Deep Learning, Stanford University on web.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/ CS 230 - Deep Learning, Stanford University on web.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/

CS 231n - Convolutional Neural Networks for Visual Recognition, Stanford University on cs231n.stanford.edu
Wrote two chapters and edited several others of two textbooks authored by my Ph.D. advisor Dr. Song-Chun Zhu, which summarize over 20 years of artificial intelligence research at UCLA: Statistical Models for Marr's Paradigm (ericmfischer.com/publication/book-1/book-1.pdf) and Stochastic Grammars for Scene Parsing (ericmfischer.com/publication/book-2/book-2.pdf)